<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-hunt-idevent-token-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-hunt-idevent-token">Identity Event Token</title>

    <author fullname="Phil Hunt" initials="P." role="editor" surname="Hunt">
      <organization abbrev="Oracle">Oracle Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <email>phil.hunt@yahoo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="William Denniss" initials="W." surname="Denniss">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Salesforce.com</organization>

      <address>
        <email>wdenniss@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    

    <author fullname="Morteza Ansari" initials="M.A." surname="Ansari">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <email>morteza.ansari@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    
    <date year="2016"/>
    <keyword>Identity</keyword>
    <keyword>Event</keyword>
    <keyword>Token</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines an Identity Event token which may
      be distributed via a protocol such as HTTP and for which an event feed
      and subscription service is described in the spec <xref target="idevent-subscription"/> </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and Overview" toc="default">
      <t>This specification defines an extensible event token format which may
      be exchanged using protocols such as HTTP. The specification builds
      on the JSON Web Token format <xref target="RFC7519"/> in order to provide a self-contained 
      message "token" that can be optionally signed using JSON Web Signature <xref target="RFC7515"/>
      and/or encrypted using JSON Web Encryption <xref target="RFC7516"/>.</t>
      <t>For the purpose of this specification an "event" is a historical statement
      of fact by a publisher that the state of a resource it controls has changed
      directly or indirectly that may be of interest to a subscriber. 
      For example, a resource has been created,
      modified, removed, or updated. In addition to direct changes of state, 
      there may be higher-level conclusions 
      made that describe an effect resulting from a change. For example, a
      publisher may wish to indicate that a new user has taken over an email
      identifier that may have been used in the past.</t>
      <t>A subscriber having 
      been informed of the event, may take its own independent action, if any, 
      within its own context. For example, having been informed of the identifier being used by someone-else,
      the subscriber may remove or ensure that the new user is not granted
      access to resources associated with the previous user.</t>
      <t>This specification is intended to be extended by other specifications. 
      It is intended to establish a common identity event format to enable inter-op
      and easier adoption of event based systems and protocols. This specification 
      does include the definition of some SCIM events. However the inclusion of 
      SCIM events is intended to be informative to other extenders and not intended 
      to replace events that may be defined for other purposes. At the time 
      of writing of this specifications there are several discussions going on around the need 
      for identity events. Some of these include:<list style="symbols">
        <t>Events to allow SCIM resource co-ordination between SCIM domains.</t>
        <t>OAuth Token Revocation (see <xref target="RFC7009"/>)</t>
        <t>OpenID Logout or downstream logout notification.</t>
        <t>Session Cancellation</t>
        <t>OpenID Risk Incident Sharing and Coordination (RISC) Events. See <xref target="RISC"/></t>
        <t>The HEART WG <xref target="HEART"/> which intends to define privacy and security related events
        in health-related data sharing APIs.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Events SHOULD NOT be used to convey commands or requests. To do so
      requires complex bi-directional signaling and error recovery mechanisms which fall
      outside the scope of this specification. The intent of this specification
      is to define a way of stating historical statements of fact that 
      subscribers may interpret for their own use.</t>
      <t>This specification is scoped to security and identity related events.
      While event tokens may be used for other purposes, the specification
      only considers security and privacy concerns relevant to identity 
      and personal information.</t>

      <section anchor="notat" title="Notational Conventions" toc="default">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>. These keywords are capitalized when used to
        unambiguously specify requirements of the protocol or application
        features and behavior that affect the interoperability and security of
        implementations. When these words are not capitalized, they are meant
        in their natural-language sense.</t>

        <t>For purposes of readability examples are not URL encoded.
        Implementers MUST percent encode URLs as described in <xref
        target="RFC3986">Section 2.1 of</xref>.</t>

        <t>Throughout this documents all figures MAY contain spaces and extra
        line-wrapping for readability and space limitations. Similarly, some
        URI's contained within examples, have been shortened for space and
        readability reasons.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="defs" title="Definitions" toc="default">
        <t>This specification uses definitions from the specification <xref target="idevent-subscription"/>.</t>
        
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="events" title="Events">
      <t>An identity event conveys a message (in the form of a token) about security subject 
      that may be of interest to a subscriber or set of subscribers participating
      in an event feed (see <xref target="idevent-subscription"/>).</t>
      <t>An event message is indicated by the attribute <spanx style="verb">schemas</spanx>
      having one value as <spanx style="verb">urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:Event</spanx>
      and more or more additional values indicating one or more event extension schema URIs.
      An event extension schema URI indicates to the reader what event information and
      event types are contained in the event message. The attribute <spanx style="verb">resourceUris</spanx> specifies
      one or more affected resources which are the subject of the event.</t>

      <t>The schema and structure of an event follows the SCIM schema model 
      as defined in <xref target="RFC7643"/>. This means that an event
      has the following aspects:<list style="symbols">
        <t>a common set of attributes common to every event, and</t>
        <t>one or more schema extensions (see Section 3 of <xref target="RFC7643"/>) 
        that each define a set of attributes that belonging to an extension.</t>
      </list> </t>
      <figure>
        <preamble>The following non-normative example shows a password change event:</preamble>
        <artwork>{  
  "schemas":[
    "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:Event",
    "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:password",
    "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:RISC:password"
  ],
  "publisherUri":"https://scim.example.com",  
  "feedUris":[
   "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754",
   "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/5d7604516b1d08641d7676ee7"
  ],  
  "resourceUris":[
    "https://scim.example.com/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9"
  ],
  "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:password":{
    "id":"44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9",
    "values":{
      "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:account:2.0:Password":{
        "resetAttempts":5
      }
    }
  },
  "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:RISC:password":{
    "terminateSession":true
  }
}</artwork>
      </figure>      
      <t>The above example shows an event that has a dual-extension and
      actually expresses a password update event. The event has a dual-extension
      which allows two different sub-events to be expressed based on one 
      state change at the publisher. Multiple events MAY be asserted at
      the same time (when appropriate), and carry different or even overlapping 
      attributes. This is expressed by placing the event extensions each within 
      its own JSON object (in this example, 
      <spanx style="verb">urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:password</spanx> and 
      <spanx style="verb">urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:RISC:password</spanx>).
      In this example, a SCIM event (see <xref target="scimEvents"/>) indicates that a password has been updated 
      and the current password reset count is 5. Notice that the value for 
      "resetAttempts" is actually part of its own schema SCIM extension 
      <spanx>urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:account:2.0:Password</spanx>.  
      </t>
      <t>The other event extension is a 
      "RISC" extension and lets a subscriber know that any current  
      sessions associated with the subject should be terminated.
      </t>
      <t>By expressing multiple extensions at the same time, the publisher
      indicates that each event type stems from the same originating event.
      Publishers MAY split a single event into multiple separate events (e.g.
      each with only one event schema extension). Publishing single-events
      may be more important when it is appropriate to minimize information 
      disclosure to a particular subscriber or set of subscribers.</t>
      
      <section title="Core Event Properties">
        <t>The following are attributes that may be included in an event
        message:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="schemas"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A multi-valued String attribute that MUST
            contains the value <spanx style="verb">urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:Event</spanx>
            and at least one other event extension URIs. </t>

            <t hangText="feedUris"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A multivalued String containing the URIs of
            the feeds the event is associated with. The publisher may
            filter these values to be only those values relevant to a
            particular subscriber. In doing so, the publisher is not
            obligated to deliver repeated events to the same subscriber.
            </t>

            <t hangText="publisherUri"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A single valued
            string containing the URI of the service provider publishing
            the event. For example, in SCIM, this is the SCIM Service Provider's root
            endpoint.</t>

            <t hangText="resourceUris"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A multi-valued
            string that contains the URIs of one or more affected resources in
            the event. For each resource URI included, the event must be
            identical. For each event extension expressed, each extension 
            MUST apply to each resourceUris value.</t>

            
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="eventMessage" title="Event Token">
        <t>An Event Token is a JWT (<xref target="RFC7519"/>)that is constructed by building a JSON
        structure (see <xref target="RFC7159"/>) that constitutes an event "message" and which is then
        used as the body of a JWT.</t>
        <t>While this specification uses JWT to convey an event message, implementers
        SHALL NOT use these events to convey authentication assertions or 
        identity tokens[[references??]].</t>
        <t><figure anchor="exampleJsonEvent" title="Example Event JSON Data">
            <preamble>The
            following is an example event message(it has been modified
            for readability):</preamble>

            <artwork>{  
  "schemas":[
    "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:Event",
    "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM"
  ],
  "publisherUri":"https://scim.example.com",  
  "feedUris":[
   "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754",
   "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/5d7604516b1d08641d7676ee7"
  ],  
  "resourceUris":[
    "https://scim.example.com/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9"
  ],
  "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:create":{
    "attributes":["id","name","userName","password","emails"],
    "values":{
      "emails":[
       {"type":"work","value":"jdoe@example.com"}
      ],
      "password":"not4u2no",
      "userName":"jdoe",
      "id":"44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9",
      "name":{
        "givenName":"John",
        "familyName":"Doe"
      }
    }  
  }
}</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>When transmitted, the above JSON body must be converted into a JWT
        as per <xref target="RFC7519"/>. In this
        example, because the event contains attribute values, the token MUST
        be encrypted per JWE (see <xref
        target="RFC7516"/>) before transmission.</t>
        <t>[[Figures below need to be updated to reflect the new message body above]]</t>
        <t><figure>
            <preamble>The following is an example of a SCIM Event expressed in
            an unsecured JWT token. The JWT header of:</preamble>

            <artwork>{"alg":"none"}</artwork>
          </figure><figure>
            <preamble>Base64url encoding of the octets of the UTF-8
            representation of the header yields:</preamble>

            <artwork>eyJhbGciOiJub25lIn0</artwork>
          </figure><figure>
            <preamble>The example JSON Event Data is encoded as
            follows:</preamble>

            <artwork>eyJwdWJsaXNoZXJVcmkiOiJodHRwczovL3NjaW0uZXhhbXBsZS5jb20iLCJmZWV
kVXJpcyI6WyJodHRwczovL2podWIuZXhhbXBsZS5jb20vRmVlZHMvOThkNTI0Nj
FmYTViYmM4Nzk1OTNiNzc1NCIsImh0dHBzOi8vamh1Yi5leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9GZ
WVkcy81ZDc2MDQ1MTZiMWQwODY0MWQ3Njc2ZWU3Il0sInJlc291cmNlVXJpcyI6
WyJodHRwczovL3NjaW0uZXhhbXBsZS5jb20vVXNlcnMvNDRmNjE0MmRmOTZiZDZ
hYjYxZTc1MjFkOSJdLCJldmVudFR5cGVzIjpbIkNSRUFURSJdLCJhdHRyaWJ1dG
VzIjpbImlkIiwibmFtZSIsInVzZXJOYW1lIiwicGFzc3dvcmQiLCJlbWFpbHMiX
SwidmFsdWVzIjp7ImVtYWlscyI6W3sidHlwZSI6IndvcmsiLCJ2YWx1ZSI6Impk
b2VAZXhhbXBsZS5jb20ifV0sInBhc3N3b3JkIjoibm90NHUybm8iLCJ1c2VyTmF
tZSI6Impkb2UiLCJpZCI6IjQ0ZjYxNDJkZjk2YmQ2YWI2MWU3NTIxZDkiLCJuYW
1lIjp7ImdpdmVuTmFtZSI6IkpvaG4iLCJmYW1pbHlOYW1lIjoiRG9lIn19fQ</artwork>
          </figure><figure anchor="eventToken"
            title="Example Unsecured Event Token">
            <preamble>The encoded JWS signature is the empty string.
            Concatenating the parts yields:</preamble>

            <artwork>eyJhbGciOiJub25lIn0
.
eyJwdWJsaXNoZXJVcmkiOiJodHRwczovL3NjaW0uZXhhbXBsZS5jb20iLCJmZWV
kVXJpcyI6WyJodHRwczovL2podWIuZXhhbXBsZS5jb20vRmVlZHMvOThkNTI0Nj
FmYTViYmM4Nzk1OTNiNzc1NCIsImh0dHBzOi8vamh1Yi5leGFtcGxlLmNvbS9GZ
WVkcy81ZDc2MDQ1MTZiMWQwODY0MWQ3Njc2ZWU3Il0sInJlc291cmNlVXJpcyI6
WyJodHRwczovL3NjaW0uZXhhbXBsZS5jb20vVXNlcnMvNDRmNjE0MmRmOTZiZDZ
hYjYxZTc1MjFkOSJdLCJldmVudFR5cGVzIjpbIkNSRUFURSJdLCJhdHRyaWJ1dG
VzIjpbImlkIiwibmFtZSIsInVzZXJOYW1lIiwicGFzc3dvcmQiLCJlbWFpbHMiX
SwidmFsdWVzIjp7ImVtYWlscyI6W3sidHlwZSI6IndvcmsiLCJ2YWx1ZSI6Impk
b2VAZXhhbXBsZS5jb20ifV0sInBhc3N3b3JkIjoibm90NHUybm8iLCJ1c2VyTmF
tZSI6Impkb2UiLCJpZCI6IjQ0ZjYxNDJkZjk2YmQ2YWI2MWU3NTIxZDkiLCJuYW
1lIjp7ImdpdmVuTmFtZSI6IkpvaG4iLCJmYW1pbHlOYW1lIjoiRG9lIn19fQ
.</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>To create and or validate a signed or encrypted event token follow
        the instructions in section 7 of <xref
        target="RFC7519"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

   



    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations" toc="default">

      <t>[[TO BE COMPLETED]]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      
      <section anchor="eventTypesRegistry" title="Event Type Registry">
        <t>[[TODO: Registration of Event Types]]</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      <reference anchor="idevent-subscription">
        
        <front>
          <title>Identity Event Subscription Protocol (work in progress)</title>
          <author fullname="Phil Hunt"><organization>Oracle Corporation</organization></author>
          <date/>
        </front>  
        <format type="TXT" target="draft-hunt-idevent-subscription-00.txt"/>    
      </reference>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?><!-- Keywords -->


      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'?><!-- URIs -->

      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'?><!-- Web Linking -->

      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml'?><!-- JSON -->
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml'?><!-- JWT -->
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7643.xml'?><!-- SCIM Schema -->
    </references>
 
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7009.xml'?><!-- OAuth Revocation -->
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml'?><!-- JWS -->
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7516.xml'?><!-- JWE -->
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7517.xml'?><!-- JWK -->

      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7644.xml'?><!-- SCIM Protocl -->
    
      <reference anchor="RISC">
        <front>
          <title>RISC (Risk and Incident Sharing and Coordination) Working Group (work in progress)</title>
          <author> <organization>The OpenId Foundation</organization></author>
          <date/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://openid.net/wg/risc/"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HEART">
        <front>
          <title>HEART Working Group (work in progress)</title>
          <author> <organization>The OpenId Foundation</organization></author>
          <date/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://openid.net/wg/heart/"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section title="Appendix A. Event Types">
      <section anchor="scimEvents" title="SCIM Events">
    
        <section anchor="scimSchemaUri" title="Event Schema URIs">
          <t>This specification defines event schema URI for SCIM. Additional event types may be
          defined using the Event Type IANA registration process described in
          <xref target="eventTypesRegistry"/>.<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:add"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified resource
            URI was added to the feed. An add does not necessarily indicate a
            resource is new or has been recently created, but rather that it
            has been added to a feed. For example, an existing user has had a
            new role (e.g. CRM_User) added to their profile which has caused
            their resource to join a feed.</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:create"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The new resource URI
            has been created at the service provider and has been added to the
            feed. When a CREATE event is sent, a corresponding ADD event is
            not issued. For example, a new user was created via HTTP POST,
            whose attribute profile met the criteria of a current feed. </t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:activate"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified
            resource (e.g. User) has been activated or is otherwise available
            for use. [TODO: this seems to be a higher level concept that may
            consist of multiple attributes changing - How to differentiate
            between activate and MODIFY events]</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:modify"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified
            resource has been updated (e.g. one or more attributes has
            changed).</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:deactivate"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified
            resource (e.g. User) has been deactivated. [TODO: Is there a
            corresponding MODIFY event?]</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:delete"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified resource has been deleted from
            the service provider and is also removed from the feed. When a
            DELETE is sent, a corresponding REMOVE is not issued.</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:remove"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified
            resource has been removed from the feed. Removal does not indicate
            that the resource was deleted or otherwise deactivated.</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:password"><vspace blankLines="0"/>The specified
            resource (e.g. User) has changed its password. If secure exchange
            is possible with the subscriber, the event may also include the
            raw password update text. A PASSWORD event MUST be transmitted in
            encrypted form (see <xref target="eventMessage"/>).</t>

            <t hangText="urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM:confirmation"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A special event that is used during
            Polling Feed Registrations and Web Callback URI subscriptions to
            confirm successful configuration of an event feed. The contents of
            a CONFIRMATION event SHALL be defined by the registration process
            documented in following sections [TODO add reference]</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="SCIM Event Attributes">
          <t>The following attributes are defined for all of the schema 
          URI defined in <xref target="scimSchemaUri"/> or any schema defined 
          within the uri namespace 
          <spanx style="verb">urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:extension:Event:SCIM</spanx>.
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="id"><vspace blankLines="0"/>An optional multi-valued 
            SCIM <spanx style="verb">id</spanx> value of the affected resource(s) 
            as defined in <xref target="RFC7643">Section 3.1</xref>. If 
            provided the identifiers MUST correspond to the values referenced
            in <spanx style="verb">resourceUris</spanx>.</t>
            <t hangText="attributes"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A multi-valued
            list of affected SCIM attributes. Each attribute listed may be a
            fully-qualified attribute name or an attribute "path" as defined
            in Figure 7 of Section 3.3.2 of <xref
            target="RFC7644"/></t>

            <t hangText="values"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A JSON object
            structure containing the affected attributes and their associated
            values. If the "values" attribute is supplied, the event message
            MUST be encrypted. Service providers SHOULD take care to ensure
            that eligible subscribers are able to see attribute values.
            Alternatively, subscribers MAY use the resourceURIs to retrieve
            the final attribute values. When doing so, the SCIM service
            provider can then assess the subscribers right to obtain the
            actual attribute values.</t>

            <t>For a password change event, the clear text password attribute
            value MAY be included in the values attribute. <spanx
            style="verb">PASSWORD</spanx> event.</t>          
          </list>
          
          </t>
          
        </section>
       
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Contributors"/>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The editor would like to thank the participants in the the SCIM
      working group for their support of this specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change Log">
      <t>Draft 00 - PH - First Draft</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
